hello I'm your host David Barnard and
this is a very special episode of the
subcl club podcast I've been at
google.io the past couple of days and we
are on campus with Sarah Kum the
managing director of app Partnerships at
Google Play on the podcast I'm going to
be talking with Sarah about how to get
Google's attention highlights from
Google IO and why hitting copy and paste
on your iOS strategy is probably not
going to work on Google Play Hey Sarah
thanks so much for joining me on podcast
today hi David I'm so grateful to be
here thank you for having me yeah and
thanks for inviting me to google.io the
last couple days have been a blast
learned so much more about Android I've
for years so many of the revenue cat
customers and people I talk to are on
Android I'm not but I'm pretty inspired
I kind of want to build an Android app
now good uh so it's really fun being
here and kind of learning way more about
the Android ecosystem all that y'all are
doing to help developers out so thanks
for inviting me of course I'm so happy
you were B to make it to Google IO it's
our annual event our Marquee developer
event and this one was a great one I'm
very energized tired and energized at
the same time I'm grateful you were here
so you could hear all the flots and yeah
so I wanted to kick things off talking
about your role at Google so tell me
what you do at Google and how you help
Google Play developers yeah sure so I
lead our Google Apps Partnerships
business development team so we work
with developers all over the world and
primarily our job is to enable them to
succeed hear their feedback on what's
working well what could be better on the
Play store and on Android overoll and
share that with our product engineering
teams and kind of build this beautiful
flywheel of f products over time I love
my job I get to talk to developers all
day hear what they're working on what
excites them what's concerning them and
take that back to the team we're a
pretty small team we are Global but we
have a limited number of people in each
region but yeah I've been doing this for
a few years now and absolutely love what
I do awesome I think the first question
every single person listening to this
podcast is going to ask is how do I talk
to Sarah and her team so I have to ask
elephant in the room how do people get
in touch with Google and get the
attention of Google yeah it's a question
we get all the time as well we try our
best to talk to as many developers as
possible so I'll say especially those
that have worked really hard their app
is really really strong and they've
scaled product Market fit we absolutely
do our best to work either oneon-one or
one to many in some form we do have some
really good resources and we have a way
to get in contact with us via support
Channel we also have an incredible play
Academy which I highly recommend to
anybody including our very mature
Partners we have so much resource there
on how to build an incredible app so we
do try to make it not required to talk
to us to be effective on play as much as
I you know my team is incredible and the
work they do is great we don't want to
make that a barrier to entry to be
successful but we do have ways to get in
touch and we'll make sure we as after
this podcast that people have those
links but yeah I'd say it's really
critical to invest in the platform
that's the best way to get our attention
yeah and that makes a ton of sense
there's hundreds of thousands of
developers maybe even Millions at this
point and millions of apps and as big as
Google is you can't staff a develop a
relations team with like 10,000 people
so it is hard and I know Apple's the
same way it's hard to get in touch but
there's a reason and it makes sense
we're all humans trying to do our best
to help people and so you can't always
get that kind of one-on-one attention
but it's cool that you do that as much
as you can because then that feedback is
super helpful and I think it's important
for people to understand to that that
feedback is getting to Google that
Google is out there talking to
developers and again unfortunately you
can't talk to every single developer so
if you're listening to this podcast and
like I want to talk to Google and you
don't ever get to talk to Google your
feedback is probably getting
communicated in other ways from other
developers and stuff like that and then
like you said we'll include in the show
notes some links to contact support and
other things and people do read that
like there is a big team getting that
kind of feedback the other elephant in
the room that everybody's going to ask
is then okay I can't necessarily just
reach out to Sarah anytime but how do I
reach out to the editorial team like how
do I get my no we do get that question a
lot we have an incredible editorial team
they work tesly they're also Global
across every region and they really work
hard to look for the best apps for the
right user at the right time you know
hidden gems they really take their craft
seriously I've discovered so many apps I
would have never found without the
editorial team so I'm very grateful for
them but similar to our team they're
very Limited in resources I'd say the
best way to get their attention the
editorial team is to build an incredible
app have a very high user rating a lot
of the features we announced to IO and
previously to use them all to really do
everything you can to make your app
meaningful delightful valuable to users
that is what we look for in featuring
because we know that typically is what
will actually work really well and users
will get very excited about those apps
so that's the number one thing like that
is a Minar you know so just everyone
should should really level set on that
and then as as possible we have
resources that again we'll link to in
the show notes where people should read
the guidelines kind of what they can do
if they want to get featured we do have
methods to make sure you're in the best
possible position it is discretion of
our editorial team and we do a lot of
user research on what we know users want
to see but yeah we absolutely love
featuring wonderful apps it's just
mutually beneficial we love to do it so
if you're listening out there and you
want to get featured look at the link
that's in the show notes and please use
it go through all the steps yeah I I was
reading that last night and I found that
link researching last night and put it
in the show notes and apple has a
similar page and it's a similar kind of
process but like if you're going to
reach out to the editorial team actually
read those things don't just send a
plank email uh read those things and try
and take off as many of those as you can
and then reach out to the editorial team
you know everybody wants to get featured
so I'm sure the editorial team is just
inundated with apps that frankly haven't
checked some of those features and so
you want to make sure that you do have a
good rating like it's just the reality
if you don't have a good rating that
there's signal there and you need to do
some work on your product so I know you
probably wouldn't want want to say that
but I'll say that I appreciate you
saying that I also will say we've tried
similar to us not being a gate to being
successful on Google Play that you don't
need to work with somebody at Google to
do that we also try to make sure
featuring is not a gate to be successful
it's wonderful we definitely love to
feature fantastic apps but we often urge
people who are so fixated on getting
featuring from the store that is
wonderful and there's so much else you
can do we announced a lot of IO
yesterday and we continue to put a lot
of work into making the store work
effective and wonderful channel of
distribution and Discovery and
engagement for all developers even if
you might not be ready for featuring or
you might not know how to go about that
so really urge everyone to not anchor
exclusively on featuring as the method
for um growth there's so many things you
can do right and something we talk about
on the podcast constantly too is like
there are thousands of ways to get
attention from affiliate marketing which
I never thought for apps but we've had
podcasts talking about how effective
that can be to influencers to press to
paid marketing to physical mailing I was
talking to somebody recently like that's
a thing again because it's actually
fairly cheap and you can be targeted and
like I haven't heard of an app doing
that but I've talked to people who've
seen that be successful in other
businesses but maybe you should
experiment with if you have a broad
market app or a more regionally focused
app like there's so many ways to get
attention I do feel like primarily
working on iOS myself and a lot of
Indies I think get this perception of
like if I can just get featured that's
going to like make or break my business
but to be honest even on iOS it's not
what it used to be you know back 10
years ago yeah getting features could be
huge but then problem with my business
and this is going to be the same for so
many developers who are like oh I'm
going to get featured and even if they
do get featured on the Google Play store
which you then realize is like oh that's
a great Spike but you still need to mark
it so like build the foundation first
you got to do the work a lot of
foundational work and continued work you
can't just rely on getting featured to
build your business 100% it's not it
should be a yes and not an either or
exactly exactly so I want to move on to
Google IO really fun being here in
person the last couple days and I think
a lot of our audience again like me
sitting here talking to somebody at
Google but our audience is often more
iOS focused and you a lot of developers
Focus their efforts and attention more
to iOS but Android is such a massive
opportunity and so for those who aren't
paying close enough attention I did want
to give some highlights from Google IO
for them to go dig in and then to also
see and contrast like Google's doing
some really cool stuff yeah but the
Google Play store has a ton of
opportunity and is innovating in a lot
of ways so I wanted to talk through some
of the announcements at Google IO do a
little highlight reel so that people can
then go dig in a little deeper but the
first thing I was super excited about is
the engage SDK so tell me what that is
is yeah so excited about the engage SDK
as well it's a pretty big shift for us
and you know I should mention that I've
been working on this team for several
years and I've seen Google Play go
through so many stages of evolution and
maturity so I'm so blessed that I've
seen that and now more than ever we're
very focused on apps we have an apps GM
meca who spoke in our play keynote
yesterday along with other incredible
speakers we also are really thinking
about the various categories within apps
and how we develop meaningful
experiences go a little ER than you know
maybe just generic apps as a category so
the engage SDK was born from this
research we found where so many users
have apps on their phone in the
multiples of tens typically above 50
above 80 in many markets and they're
just not using them as regularly as they
should I think we can all relate to this
um you got just like a lot a lot of
icons and at some point you probably had
a very relevant use case and then you
forget to go back maybe even the same
problem comes up in your life again but
you just kind of oh I forgot that I
installed that app you know 6 months ago
and talking to Partners and developers
like my team does many developers don't
have a use case that needs to be daily
you know some apps are daily use and
that's the intention some will not be
daily or if they are daily you might
just miss some of that content so we
knew that was a problem we wanted to
help solve and we thought through like
what does that look like what could we
be doing differently and so the engage
SDK is a way for developers to share
with us on device in a very personalized
and private way content that's relevant
to the user on that device so for you
you know your feed in YouTube might be
one example or what you recently bought
in a shopping app that kind of thing to
just provide you a little bit of
contextual information and gather that
up in clusters that make sense depending
on the use case if it's a social use
case or shopping whatever it might be
that we know users tend to kind of think
about their apps in different groups so
that's what it was born out of we
announced at IO that it's now in
developer preview and anyone can go
follow the link and start building for
it which we're very excited for and we
already have some fantastic partners
that we announced on stage Spotify Uber
e McDonald's Tik Tok many others and so
I'm super pumped of how this is going to
evolve really our mission is to bring
that content that your all building all
the developers that are listening to
this to the Forefront and show
contextual personal information on a
regular basis so that users don't have
to go hunt in their wall of AD icons and
instead it will just come to them in
this experience so very excited for what
we're doing with engage SDK so I got a
little sneak peek and I know it's not
coming till later this year but I'm
excited
aome again another thing that makes you
want to build an Android app because
this looks really cool and things like
Tik Tok and Twitter and YouTube they
kind of have this natural draw you're
standing in line at a grocery store and
you want to kill some time and you get
drawn into those things but of course
more and more as a society we realize
that's probably not the best thing for a
human to just be consuming dopamine hits
constantly and and what's really cool
about the way this is designed and the
way it's going to be surfaced throughout
the OS
is that it maybe kind of breaks that
chain a little bit there's an app
Headway that has this really great ads
like stop Doom scrolling and learn
instead they kind of summarize books and
it's an easy way to get some bite-size
insights that actually benefit your life
versus like Doom strolling Tik Tok or
whatever I mean Tik toks a great I don't
want to totally throw them under the bus
but I think a lot of us find we engage
too much with those what excites me
about this is like it's going to surface
apps and context and features
that maybe people should be interacting
with more but that don't have that kind
of natural draw that you're standing in
line and think to do and so I think it's
going to be a really great feature not
just for like developers to get people
back into their apps but also just to
help people diversify their experience
and maybe get some of those more
meaningful experiences on their device
brought to them and having those
triggers to go back to those things
instead of it getting lost in the sea of
apps and not even remembering ABS I mean
we definitely our goal is to help users
be more intentional it's really part of
Google's mission is very much about
access to information useful information
at scale and this is one way where
instead of you on autopilot kind of like
you mentioned going to your phone and
maybe just missing out on so much of the
additional things you can do there and
maybe just defaulting to the same
behaviors what if you see everything
that might be relevant to you that maybe
just wouldn't be top of mind to your
point because of just the nature of that
app not being as frequent potentially
and you are in control you can see what
you want to access what's relevant to
you and then go a level deep and again
back to my team and what we care about
making sure developers are getting that
benefit um and seeing that traffic back
into their apps also having full access
and control over what is shown to the
user it's very personal on device yeah I
do think there's some strong element of
intentionality here to help users really
use their phone as a supercomputer and
take advantage of the full Corpus of
insight and data and services on it yeah
Switching gears a little there was a lot
about the Google Play Commerce
capabilities and I wanted to kick that
section off talking about the continued
expansion of payment options I think
this is something that's lost on a lot
of folks especially people who are like
web web web we need to like pay on the
web well Google has 190 markets
supported 165 carrier billing options
300 different local payment options like
the Commerce capab like the ease of
payment on Google Play is something the
teams have been putting a ton of effort
into to make it so much easier for
people to pay which is what you want as
a like you want to make it as easy as
possible and users to purchase and
Google Play has been doing a ton of work
on that front we have I'm so happy to
appreciate you saying that I am so
excited about what we announced and I
mentioned this to you you know I think
harisha leads that team we work very
closely on developer feedback constantly
are listening to the ecosystem what's
working what could be better what forms
of payment they want what features in
the flow and the by flow would be useful
to them so everything we announced I
just as a giddy kid like I was listening
like yeah that's what this developer
wanted or that developer wanted or oh we
for the last year we've been talking
about this so I've never been prouder
than yesterday every single feature that
we announced was very much based on
feedback from from the ecosystem and
yeah we announced new payment forms in
Brazil pix which is a huge payment form
there super popular that it's now
available on Google Play billing and in
India we've expanded UPI options also
similarly the incredibly popular form of
payment in India and we also added new
ways to pay like installment payments
Which is popular not just in Brazil but
also in several European markets we've
made that available we're really working
on not just access so anyone can pay
more effectively using the form of
payment they want and better ways to
make sure the buy flow is relevant if
you're a student you can now pay or as a
developer you can set student plans
senior plans so many things we announced
have just been in the works for a while
they're not easy it's yeah you alluded
to it takes us a lot of time a lot of
resource this is somewhere we definitely
invest across Google as well but yeah
we're very proud of the payments
platform we also announced over 200
million subscribers across all of our
Corpus of apps in the ecosystem so
really proud of the work the team is
doing there yeah so you mentioned
installment payments when that was
announced I think in the developer
keynote I thought and then I saw tweets
and other things it's like wait a minute
that's just a
subscription but it's not and then it
like took me a minute to kind of realize
how cool that actually was is that one
there's countries like India where there
are heavy regulations against recurring
subscriptions because it can be
problematic and people are taking
advantage of it and personally I think
there should be more and more regulation
about making it easy to unsubscribe and
giving users more control because when
you're have the capability to
automatically take money from somebody's
account that's a weighty responsibility
and so I believe in it as a software
developer as an effective monetization
tool that benefits both users and
developers by incentivizing that
continued investment but it doesn't work
for everyone it doesn't work in every
country it can be problematic and so
installments are a way to have a
nonrecurring subscription but that isn't
such a big like for a lot of people
upfront paying 60 bucks can be a huge
hit to their budget absolutely so yeah
tell me more I mean I'm Jing on cuz I I
love the space so yeah I feel like we
could talk all day about subscriptions
so you're totally right that it's both
about being creative and making sure
we're being thoughtful and not everyone
in the world subscribes the same way and
not everyone in the world wants to
subscribe at all you know installment
payments like you mentioned is not just
popular in Brazil for users who might
feel the sticker shock of a large amount
it's actually just the way to pay I mean
even if you can afford it it's kind of
or that you're not thinking too much
about the actual price it's just the
methodology that people tend to prefer
you know it's something we've been
investing in for many many years we
launched our subscription Center I think
we were one of the first platforms to
have a subscription Center and we were
very bullish on easy ways to cancel and
I do remember I have to share this
because it's accurate when we had that
kind of easy cancel button that where
you didn't have to call a human you know
those you know there was like this time
where you had to call constantly to and
unfortunately still happens in many
situations and we were very strict that
like nope there's going to be a button
and we're not going to allow if
developers say hey I don't like this
button and we got a lot of feedback from
our partners saying I want you to remove
that button it's it's increasing my
churn and on other platforms my churn is
better and I think it's because of that
button and we were very firm on it they
like nope we're very we hear from users
and to your point unfortunately there
are some bad actors out there who really
try to dupe users into recurring
payments on things they didn't even know
they were paying for so we've always
been really passionate about not just
like we love subscriptions we think
that's such a fast growing space there's
so much Innovation happening and we
announced some of that too on how to
think about different price points
different plans all of that but also to
be really careful that you got to build
that trust first if us don't feel like
you're going to give them an easy way to
cancel or they think you're going to
renew in the background without telling
them it can just do a world of harm we
take that really seriously yeah a couple
other cool things in the payment space
that I thought were really interesting
was ask someone else to pay that's so
cool and I know it came out of the
family purchase which I actually use
with my kids like they have to ask to
buy they actually even have to ask to
download which I love that as a parent
but ask somebody else to buy you can ask
anybody
bu divers of pment might ask a friend if
you're using the app and they were like
hey you really need to get this app and
you're like okay you pay for it and now
on Android can be like you send them the
link and they pay for it yeah I think
again we really try to listen to what
our users are telling us what our
developers are telling us and because
we're such a global platform we
announced we have over 2.5 billion
active users across the world we find
these interesting patterns where people
don't behave the way somebody in the Bay
Area you know my behave with with how
they pay so yeah that came out of our
feedback on you know this is something
we've been looking for same with some of
the various plans we announced yesterday
on student plans and Senior plans so I'm
really excited about it I think when
whenever we announce these features I
think of it as growing the pie of
options yeah and that is only good for
different types of developers different
regions and use cases and you kind of
dropped it in there but I I wanted to go
deeper on the student plan thing that
was another thing that I think super
cool you there is talk about how tough
it is to monetize some of these younger
users high schoolers college students
they don't have the kind of disposable
income that career professionals have
and so being able to have a flow inside
Android that verifies you're a student
and then when you're no longer a student
you no longer get like that's really
cool it is very cool and I love that
we're allowing a flow for when you're no
longer a student that you can quickly
move to the next non-student plan in a
seamless way as well so you don't turn
out that user yeah it's such a critical
area for us you know you saw a lot of
what we announced at Google IO not just
on playing Android but more broadly
centers around learning and students are
a huge part of that so we're absolutely
a company of Learners it's I feel like
we're a little bit like University so is
a lot we do for students because we know
it's such a critical space And We R all
students one day in some form and we
know that like you said it's not always
easy to pay for really meaningful apps
especially now with Gen apps there's so
many useful apps that you know we know
students should be using so we're
hopeful that a lot of developers take
advantage of student plans yeah that's
super cool and then similarly having
students have to verify that they're a
student and then that student status
expiring you'll also introduce some
tools to help developers prevent price
Arbitrage so not only can you not
pretend to be a student but if you're in
the US you can't pretend you're in India
and get a discounted price I never even
thought about that but again like Google
operates at such a large scale around
the world that you probably seeing the
data these like price Arbitrage of
people using vpns and stuff so now
Google Play tools to help prevent this
kind of price Arbitrage yeah definitely
and that's something we have seen on our
end quite a bit like you mentioned we're
a very Global business we operate you
know across so many billions of users
and so many markets so one thing we've
done is when we're noticing uh a higher
propensity of Arbitrage if a currency is
fluctuating we know developers will have
especially those that maybe offer at
scale lots of Ip will have to scramble
to figure out oh how do I handle this
and that's not the kind of thing we want
our developers spending a lot of time on
it's not ideal
really complex to solve complex and
difficult so we know that's something we
think is a platform we can really help
developers to address that and just take
that stress out of their days and handle
it as much as we can on the platform
level so I think that's a mindset we
generally take we don't want developers
to have to worry about things that we
can help solve and make better on a
platform level yeah another thing that
is so much harder for developers to do
but is something the platform can do a
better job at is a new feature device
recall is that people will wipe their
device and like get free trial every
seven days figure out way another kind
of Arbitrage of like redo the free trial
over and over again and so now there's
ways in a privacy focused way to prevent
those kind of things as well yeah
absolutely I mean again we know some
people will Factor reset we can address
that and that not be an issue for
developers and again we're just trying
to make sure as a developer when you're
getting subscribers when you're getting
people buying your products and using
your products we want them to be
well-intentioned the users that you're
trying to Target and that you have the
right safeguards in place to make sure
you're not having to do a ton of extra
work to ensure you have the right users
coming for the right reasons right and
the last thing from Google Play that I
wanted to highlight again another thing
that's really cool is that you can now
create custom Play Store listings
targeted on keyword so in the past
there's been deep links to the custom
there's been a lot of options for these
custom Play Store pages and now you can
Target based on keywords so excited
about about this we've been investing a
lot in our custom store listings adding
more features so that you as a developer
can experiment can customize the actual
store listing based on the audience and
this is another way that I think we hope
will help developers to maximize the
value of the organic traffic they're
getting search is such an important part
of the Play Store we're search company
we have Decades of experience in Search
and we know how important it is to make
sure if I find your app based on a
certain keyword search that you might
want to show me a very different custom
store listing experiment to maximize my
conversion so so excited we're also
suggesting the keywords that are
important ones for you to customize
based on I'm really excited and I hope
more developers will take advantage of
this so that they can really boost their
conversion rate yeah and the Google
keynote was many jokes made about it ai
ai ai Gemini Gemini Gemini so there's
been a lot of talk about AI this week
and broadly this year what are some of
the ways you think Google Play
developers can leverage AI in the most
impactful ways I do feel like can be a
distraction it can lead you down paths
that maybe aren't optimal for your
business so I know you and your team
talk to a ton of developers and this has
been a hot topic for over a year now so
what are some of the top ways you think
that AI can help developers and actually
increase business instead of kind of
leading them down rabbit holes that
aren't going to actually benefit them I
think that's a really good point that AI
is a tool and it's a super powerful very
exciting tool and now with the power of
the models especially the custom models
the multimotor models there's so much
more you can do as a developer to either
decrease your time spent on something
that maybe you could be a lot more
efficient with or maximize the value the
experience for the user so I'm really
excited about it I do think you're spot
on that where you use AI in your
business whether it's user facing or
internal needs to start with what
problem you're solving and if there
isn't a real problem that you're solving
either for the user or your business
probably not the place to use AI or
probably anything really you know you
shouldn't be in the business of building
demos for users but I think for what
we've heard from many of our partners
and the developers at large developer
ecosystem on where they're finding
success with AI a lot on content
creation I think back to custom store
listings a few years ago if you were to
have to customize based on so many
variables keywords regions AdWords
campaign everything in that nature
you're going to have a team who's like
doing a ton of custom creation of assets
and testing those out it is important
work what if that team could be using
tools and therefore they can spend their
time on the more complex work of
understanding what's working and use
those tools to create those assets in a
faster way and often those assets can be
created you know even better with more
riffs with tools so I think a lot of it
on content Creation in all ways and
forms we're seeing feedback that it's
been very successful still requires a
lot of human verification and hopefully
that goes back into your model whatever
model you're using so you can get better
over time I think another space we're
seeing a lot of success is in helping
the customer experience both the
customer feedback and any support
systems that you might have as a
developer but also just making sure
you're asking in a contextual way for
feedback getting feedback loops from the
customer there are some areas I think
we're seeing slower adoption like
whenever it's user facing I think
there's some concerns of is this going
to be good we don't want to denigrate
trust but that's said I think it's just
the beginning I think there's so many
exciting things that we're seeing many
of our partners adopt and also seeing as
a system we're seeing usage in really
interesting areas so yeah whether it's
on device models that we announced in
the keynote the content creation
multimodal models especially if you're a
video creator back to you know kind of
making sure you're engaging your users
across the whole funnel there so many
ways you can use AI but it needs to
start with the problem that you're
solving don't just throw AI in the app
and so you can put AI in the keywords
like yeah not a good idea or not
suain I want to switch gears and talk
more specifically about how developers
can succeed on the Play Store I know
that's what you and your team Focus so
much on and the first thing I wanted to
talk through is what you've been seeing
so something you were telling me about
is a on a global scale this is something
I've been saying on the podcast for a
while but then hearing it from you you
actually have the global data and the
user level data to be able to actually
see how this is playing out but I've
been saying for a long time you know Bas
anecdotally people talk about
subscription to fatigue and things like
that and then I'm looking at the revenue
cat data saying we see so many apps
growing and like the pies growing and so
I've kind of anecdotally saying it seems
like more and more people are will
willing to pay for digital goods and
services and more and more people are
willing to pay via subscriptions but it
all kind of felt anecdotal but you see
the data we see the data absolutely and
you're spot on we're seeing
subscriptions growth both in net overall
but also in buyer numbers people are
subscribing scale to lots of different
apps and use cases you know I do think
there is something to be said about
making sure you're matching the value to
the subscription you're offering so I
think often when we hear subscription
fatigue that could be maybe a incorrect
way to say maybe there's the value is
off or people don't feel like that's
worth paying for and we are really
investing and encouraging developers to
think Beyond subscriptions if because
many especially us developers tend to
offer only subscriptions and we think
that especially on Android where we've
got such a broad range of users and
different markets different device types
it doesn't work for everybody kind of
back to what we were talking about with
installment payments and other forms of
payments so we definitely don't think
it's a yes end you know subscriptions
are growing what a wonderful way to grow
your business there's so many benefits
to that and there are other ways you can
reach users maybe even diverse users
that you would not have reached
otherwise if you can think beyond the
monthly or the annual subscription in
that white paper that we're going to
link to in the show notes one of the
things that really stood out to me to
the point you just made is that in the
white paper it show that us-based
developers are more likely to lean on
subscriptions but the developers in Asia
in other parts of the world who actually
understand their markets better better
you see in the data and there's pie
charts and things in this white paper
showing that developers outside the US
are actually kind of leading the way in
diversifying the way to pay like in the
US consumers are more willing to pay via
subscription it is one of the biggest
markets but it's interesting to see that
developers in other countries actually
know that's not always going to work
yeah totally I mean that's what I love
about play and Android in my job that
you kind of learn from others there's so
much that we think we know about how
users want to pay or how apps should be
built and then we just you know it gets
turned on our head sometimes which is a
really wonderful thing so yes you're
spot on I think in what we found in Asia
Pacific more users are interested in a
diverse way to pay usually iip often a
blend of subscriptions and iip whereas
in the US it typically has been the case
that people launch with subscriptions
businesses and scale those maybe offer
more plans but rarely will brunch out
into IP in addition and the interesting
thing is that the developers who are
based out of Asia Pacific and who have
been more willing to experiment with
subscriptions in iip actually tend to
find really good success in the US so
you know it's a really little known fact
that the US is one of the largest mid to
entry level device markets for Android
it's you know there's this mindset that
the US is you know everyone's on a
premium device but that's just not true
so we do find that developers who are
willing to experiment with either a
hybrid of I and subscriptions or more
iip will tend to actually do very well
in the US there are more people with
different devices different preferences
who might not be willing to pay for an
annual subscription but they might do a
7-Day pass or a standalone consumable
for a specific product so yeah we do see
this big Regional difference and I'm
glad you mentioned the white paper very
proud of the team our Consulting team
that worked on that we have really
wonderful researchers and Consultants
who go deeper into these topics so I
want to dive deeper into diversifying
red ven streams and hybrid monetization
but before we get there I did want to
take a step back and talk about how
different the Play Store is than iOS and
I think too many people it's like they
know it's different but there's still
kind of a tendency to copy and paste
their iOS strategy and think it's going
to work on Android and this is part of
it is the diversification of payments
but the Play Store Works differently the
people are different the devices are
different the willingness to pay is
different like there's some pretty big
differences between the iOS market and
the Android markeet and when you're on
both platforms like a lot of developers
who say they can't find success on
Android some of that is maybe that they
aren't spending enough time to really
understand those differen any key things
that you think developers should be
thinking about yeah absolutely I mean
this is a really big topic and something
that we talk a lot about on the team how
can we reduce those barriers to
understanding an entry and help
developers to build for play in a
different way and I think one thing
we've noticed in our data is there's so
many devices on Android there's a huge
spectrum of you've got the $2,000 device
you made the latest s device from
Samsung or a $200 device that somebody
got and it works very well but it
doesn't have the same spec as a very
high-end device and the users who are on
the more premium devices actually behave
quite similarly to those on iOS or other
premium skew heavy platforms so if
you're only targeting those users then
potentially the same behaviors will work
with some swaps to the features but you
know if you're really targeting a
premium user there might be one skew
that you build for that or you know you
just generally keep your aperture a
little more narrow but that will not get
you the full benefit and the beauty of
playing Android where you've got 2.5
billion people around the world and many
for whom this is their first Computing
device their only Computing device and
their preferences are going to look
different and so we absolutely do
encourage anyone building for play on
Android to think bigger and to think
about the bigger diversity of users that
you can reach so whether it's I think
really it comes down to the full funnel
thinking through how am I going to
Target my message how am I going to
offer different features and services
and value that can really more broadly
it doesn't mean that you have to offer
too many bells and whistles you know
like every single thing in the app but
tailor that depending on device type on
region and especially price points and
different skews whether it's
subscriptions or iip even just different
plans um depending on the user and what
your signals are telling yourself that
they might want so I think that's really
critical and we've seen that in our work
that the developers who take that time
and do that little bit of extra leg room
to understand like oh this is a
different platform it's more diverse 's
more to do they reap a lot more rewards
than those that don't so I want to dive
deeper into a lot of things you
mentioned and you mentioned specifically
that and we've been talking about this
like diversification of revenue streams
and there's a lot of different ways that
can happen and so one of the top things
and not only are there a lot of ways
that that can happen there's kind of
stages to it as well yes and so for a
small team thinking about all the
different skew and we we'll get to that
and talk more deeply about how to
package all the different SK and stuffff
but even for the early developers the
lowest hanging fruit is to experiment
with pricing and packaging and maybe
even layering in some consumables how do
you think about how developer should
start the kind of baby steps to like
expanding into the diversification of
Revenue it's a great point because yeah
if you're a subscription developer who
has maybe one tier potentially two but
kind of you've got like one plan a
Premium plan and that's what you're
working with jumping straight from that
to like let me build a virtual currency
ecosystem might be quite a bit to take
on it's possible but not going to be
easy your spot on that we definitely
recommend the low hanging fruit of
testing pricing and tiers is a good
place to start and that's something that
you know we often see for example
especially in content heavy spaces so
media entertainment books music that
there is some anxiety to go outside of
the boundaries of kind of this Premium
plan a lot to do with the unit economics
of the content that you might be
providing as a developer a lot to do
with just Norms of competitors but what
we find is that if you can just think
about what works for you it's not what
your competitor is doing or what another
industry is doing might not be the right
fit to start to test to pick apart you
know what might be a better Fit For A
7-Day pack like a starter pack for your
app if you're a music app or an audio
app maybe offering like a few podcasts
as a consumable and if that works and
people want more then maybe thinking
through okay how might this fit into my
broader Premium plan so absolutely agree
that if you're early to this
experimentation phase to start with
pricing and plans and see what works and
to be as open as you can to weekly
subscriptions is something we see a lot
of success with in some regions but not
too many developers using it especially
out of the US in addition to prepaid
plants so it's not really a subscription
but another way to Market a subscription
to a user so that they don't feel that
burden of I got to commit for a whole
year to this product yeah we were
talking about this earlier and it's the
kind of thing that might actually work
really well for AI apps because they do
have such a high cost of goods is that
instead of offering a 7-Day free trial
maybe you offer a 7day pass that's two
bucks and if there's a really low
barrier to entry and the user sees a lot
of value then you kind of get them in at
this cheaper price and then if they do
see a ton of value that's the on-ramp to
the subscription rather than just
offering a free trial which may end up
being very expensive to deliver
especially when your cost is high and so
yeah thinking through some of these and
that's a fairly low Hing free like it's
not that hard to create a 7day pass and
offer that instead of a 7day free trial
like there's a lot of this kind of
experimenting and pricing and packaging
I did experiment my weather app just
showing the monthly price as a default
so in my app you just see one price and
then there's a button to see all the
plans so I did an experiment seeing the
$4 a month plan does that increased
conversion compared to seeing the $40 a
year plan turns out 20% increase in paid
subscribers
by them just seeing four anchoring right
they see $4 like oh that's cheap funny
enough I ran the experiment through
Revenue cat and I've been tracking the
data and I'm going to actually lose
money so even though I got a 20%
increase in conversion those monthly
subscribers are turning so I switched it
back to the $40 plan because that is
going to maximize Revenue but it was
just super low hanging fruit experiment
and to see that lower price point was
really attractive and did leave to more
users even though it didn't maximize LTV
for me and those are kind of things that
people should be experimen I love that I
love that you took the time to look at
the full analysis of the data how it
impacted your LTV and we're open to just
trying out new things I think that's
exactly what we're encouraging um the
ecosystem to do it's not so much to
absolutely have as many tiers as
possible and consumables and and a
virtual coin currency of your own it's
really getting into that habit that
muscle of continuously experimenting try
tracking what's working and what's not
based on your goals again and if you are
Global which I hope many of you are
listening are because that's the beauty
of mobile development being very aware
that what works in one market or works
for one set of users especially on
Android is very likely to not work as
well outside that group so just to be
much more Nimble and test as much as you
can yeah and your team has been thinking
a lot about and sharing about and we
talked about it kind of framework to
think about these experiments through is
maximizing the points along the demand
curve like some people are willing to
play a small amount but there's a lot of
people willing to pay a small amount
right and there's a small number of
people who are willing to pay a lot
right and kind of finding ways so as
you're experimenting with these hybrid
monetization and different pricing and
maybe a paid trial instead of a free
trial it's looking for ways to maximize
all the points on that demand curve like
meet people where they are for their
willingness to pay right and a lot of us
probably are leaving money on the table
not experimenting on the high end of
things it's like offering a super
premium tier offering additional ways to
pay yeah we've seen a lot in our data
for example the majority of users who
will purchase in an app including
subscriptions and Beyond tend to wait
over a year before they make their
purchase that is a very common flow so
which I was very surprising to us I
think you know we had assumed like oh
everyone's just going to wake up install
their app and then immediately get
convinced by the value proposition and
purchase and I think what that Insight
told us and it does differ a little bit
by vertical and type of app use case but
it's generally there's a big audience
out there that won't be convinced in the
first few days of your app that they're
willing to pay but they will be one day
and that data is exactly what we see so
yeah exactly to your point picking up as
many signals as you can through your own
understanding of what your app offers
your own audience analytics and then
thinking through what might be the right
offer for this user based on their
pattern are they a merry coming in every
now and then somebody who might be
shopping around for different apps in
this use case that you might have a
different approach for that kind of user
versus like you said somebody might be a
power user really engaged and you might
be leaving value on the table with them
you're not offering them enough you
maybe they're monthly subscriber but
there's more that they're very willing
to pay for so absolutely I think there's
this mindset that I either have to get
someone to pay or they're free and if I
don't do that in the first couple of
weeks then I'm missing out I've got a
low conversion rate and I think we're
seeing that that's kind of maybe the old
mobile world and I think of the more
sophisticated developers that we're
seeing greater success are thinking much
longer term and bigger picture in terms
of the segments of Their audience and
probably again stage you know an early
stage app maybe does need to push really
hard on that early mization and maybe
they can't play that long game but then
to see that that is an opportunity I was
shocked when I saw those numbers that so
many people do subscribe after a year so
premium can be and is a very powerful
strategy get the habituation show them
some value and eventually bring them
into the paying fold exactly exactly one
of the things we've been talking about
but haven't really gone super deep in is
consumables like it some ways it's kind
of the ultimate way to meet people along
the demand curve and I feel like Tinder
I've talked about this a lot as a great
example of that is that those
consumables really give the people who
are want to pay more who are super
engaged who can pay more the ability to
pay more but that's probably not the
best fit for app so how has your team
seen consumables be used most
effectively to kind of meet people at
different points in that demand curve
yeah and you're spot on the Tinder a lot
of dating apps have seen great success
with both iip and the hybrid model where
if you're a subscriber you might even
get unique access to certain consumables
that are good fit for you you know we
are seeing more it's funny you say that
maybe some people would think that's not
a fit for their business and I'm going
to say something radical right now so
bear with me I think it could be a fit
for any one's business and I think
there's something out there that is a
good fit for consumable it's just about
thinking through what's the right way
for you to do it and when to your point
on maturity that's not something we'd
recommend to like if you're very early
stage and you're a subscription model a
year or two in that might not be the
right time to think about adding a whole
bunch of I AP and I'll give an example I
think what we've seen out of a lot of
developers in Korea and Japan that are
in the web Novel Web tune or comic space
so huge industry and actually it's
really growing in the US we see a lot of
Young Americans loving that kind of
content and using using a lot of those
apps on their phone and that industry
used to be a little bit more
subscription heavy and similar to many
other content Industries kind of this
model where you're subscribing and
getting you know whatever it is your
access for a monthly period or an annual
period and what we found is that many
web tunes and web novel developers are
experimenting with their own virtual
currencies with a hybrid of iip and
subscriptions and seeing really good
success especially when thinking through
like you said earlier the high value
users who might have a higher appetite
for a certain IP there more they can
offer there and they have that content
and they can even be creative with what
they Source from their own creators the
artists so I think there's so many ways
any business could approach iip it is
something to think about when you're in
a more mature stage if you're a
subscriptions business because it it is
complicated we're very bullish on
learning from other Industries you know
obviously gaming is by far the most IAP
Centric industry I think there's a lot
apps can learn from both obviously from
gaming but also from dating from comics
from web novels who and social also have
been experimenting a lot more with iip
because it can be a really good way to
engage your valuable users and to offer
them more chances to build that trust
and that buy in with your app like you
said earlier people want to pay we're
seeing that propensity increase over
time so giving them the options to do
that in a way that works for them is a
smart thing to do so speaking of gaming
you a lot of people talk about
gamification of apps and we have seen
huge example dualingo is a great example
of bringing a level of gamification into
the app but you also mentioned like
tipping and Coins and Collectibles and
stuff like that actually met yesterday
might ended up having him on the podcast
he was a hoot to talk to the founder of
Run pee the app where tells you when in
a movie you can go pee where you're not
going to miss a big plot twist or
something and he actually said they
moveed to fully tipping and he's making
more money than ever and that people
just love the app so much and he
presents it in a very like you know help
us create this content and he was saying
they get surprisingly large tip
and so point being with this whole
conversation has been about like
diversifying monetization and
gamification tipping coins collectible
like there's so many ways to do that so
any lwh hanging fruit there that you
think people should be exploring yeah we
are seeing huge growth in tipping
whether that's through a coin economy or
just yeah some iip that you can offer at
various price points and we're seeing it
mostly in live streaming and social and
to your point though we're seeing that
expand we've noticed this trend where
creater economy apps really started the
most fast growing ones tended to be in
video Creations some YouTube and Discord
Tik Tok that kind of app and we're now
seeing that model expand more and more
into different areas in Industries for
example there's this trend that we're
seeing coming out of a lot of Greater
China based apps called Drama shorts
which is these short form videos they're
definitely worth checking out some of
these apps they're very fun to watch
very engaging almost like the days of
our LIF style like dramatic and a lot of
their content and their monetization
models are akin to to games you know a
lot of iip a lot of time based things
and on tipping you're absolutely right
that we're seeing more developers
experiment with tipping outside of the
traditional social live streaming I mean
it definitely is something to I think
continue experimenting with it kind of
depends on the problem you're trying to
solve for the user back to like the
problem and the value that they're going
to get but absolutely that's something
that we think has got a huge bright
future we're seeing growth in these
types of business models at a faster
rate and that's part of the reason we
announced also yesterday that we're
increasing our price limits I think to
like 99 99 because we know that there's
demand and and some users are absolutely
very into these creators and have a lot
of love for them and the content they're
making and want to tip so it is a really
important space it's fast growing and I
think Creator economies have this
beautiful symbiosis where often it's
creating a a space for these smaller
creators we call them professional user
generated content where you're not going
to have your goal is not even
necessarily to become the next whatever
it might be you know major Studio major
artist major Etc sometimes it is but
sometimes it's not sometimes you do want
to remain a kind of a professional state
but in a smaller scale and this allows
you to have a business and run that
business not just for video creators but
for all types of creators out there the
last topic I wanted to bring up from the
white paper and it was really cool again
that yall shared a white paper and
shared a bunch of data and I know the
team's looking to share more and more
data over time but you mentioned
secondary product Market fit and the
fact that apps that find solid secondary
product Market fit
have almost triple the minutes with
their daily active users and almost
double the daily active user to monthly
active user ratio and you we saw this
with col a great example again Pioneer
big app in the space is that when they
expanded from meditation into sleep
stories it wasn't this dramatic like
bolt on a whole another feature set but
it was a very natural extension of the
product but it was a very strong
secondary product Market fit that kind
of unlocked new growth for them I
haven't talked to Comm and gotten any
data on this or anything but from what
we see broadly it seems like that
created a new inflection point in their
growth and I would imagine similarly
they probably saw increased engagement
more daily active users you know there's
a trigger right we were talking about
earlier it's like a trigger I need to go
to sleep oh now I'm going to use calm to
sleep whereas maybe meditation it's like
oh I know I should meditate but I don't
have time today and so that was a way to
not only create secondary product Market
fit but create this secondary trigger to
bring people back in the app so what are
you seeing be successful in this
secondary product Market fit yeah I
think absolutely I love that you know
this is data that we so corroborated by
what our instincts were were hopefully
telling us that like if you I think what
con did really well and John tend their
CPO I think speaks about this really
thoughtfully they're out to solve a set
of user problems that actually have some
common symptoms potentially where you
know I'm not sleeping well maybe I have
some anxiety I'm a new parent I'm not
sleeping well cuz I have young kids they
contined to to think very holistically
about that instead of thinking you know
another way to think about your product
is I'm a live streaming app or I'm a
meditation app and that can be a lot
more restrictive and isn't actually what
your users are coming to you for they're
coming because they have a problem
there's a great quote that Andy dun
often uses I think it's attributed to
Peter duer originally that the consumer
rarely buys what you think you sell and
I think it's a very accurate Trend that
we see in the apps in the store that
often the reason that somebody's coming
to your app has a a multitude of ways
you can solve for that problem and to
not feel restricted to I'm only going to
offer streaming video or I'm only going
to offer a social text based interaction
from a design perspective we're very
supportive of clarity and like a clear
user proposition and clear onboarding
all of the above and I think con does
that very well but yeah absolutely we do
see that if you can solve that problem
in multiple ways and offer more
diversity of content on how to do that
because not everyone's the same and some
people might want to listen to something
without video some people might want
only video some people might want a
transcript like if you can be more again
to diversity of different users and
different ways of interacting you can be
big picture thinking about the problem
you're solving we see a lot more success
so yeah we see that across the board of
every type of user behavior that if you
offer more than one way to solve that
problem you'll see better success yeah
very cool well as we wrap up anything
else you wanted to share with the sub
Club listeners I'm so grateful that you
had me on I'll just plug for a second
that a lot of us on the team are huge
fans of your podcast and we love
listening to it and you often have a lot
of the guests you have are people we
work with and really love the insights
that you share so thank you for the work
you do I think it's rising the tide of
the entire ecosystem and so happy about
that I'll share that we publish content
as much as we can we're trying to get
more insights out there into the
ecosystem so if you want to learn more
about what we're up to especially a lot
of the iio announcements check out our
blog check out our X feed YouTube
channel all of the above to find out the
latest and yeah very excited for
everyone to give feedback on the
features we announced to IO the past
couple of days and to test them out
thanks so much for doing this this is so
much fun thank you so much for having me
David
[Music]
thanks so much for listening if you have
a minute please leave a review in your
favorite podcast player you can also
stop by chat. sub club.com to join our
private community
[Music]